Guide to the Birmingham Union Collection, 1893-1977 AIS.1978.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Birmingham Union Collection
1893-1977
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Birmingham Union (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1978.10
2.35 Linear Feet (3 boxes, 9 oversize files, 2 reels microfilm)
The Birmingham Union began when a group of concerned citizens decided to promote the revitalization and historic preservation of the South Side in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. This collection contains information gathered by this group concerning the historic development and attempted revitalization of the South Side. The collection includes publications, news clips, histories, and photographs that contain information on churches, organizations, societies, institutions, and individuals in the South Side. The historic material covers the late-nineteenth and early-twentieth centuries, and the focus then moves to South Side events during the 1950's - 1970's.
History
The Birmingham Union was a community organization began in 1976 in order to promote the historical and cultural significance of Pittsburgh's South Side (formerly called Birmingham). The organization worked with the South Side Local Development Company, the Pittsburgh History and Landmarks Foundation, the South Side Community Council, and the South Side Chamber of Commerce to save the Victorian character of the South Side's shopping and entertainment district. They produced several promotional publications and organized community events. Through their efforts, the National Trust for Historic Preservation designated East Carson Street as a "Great American Main Street." Mary Jane Schmalstieg and Dr. Bosanka Evosevic served as directors for the organization during the 1970s.
Arrangement
Series I. Organizational/Research Files
Series II. Microfilm
Series III. Photographs, Negatives and Slides
Scope and Content Notes
This collection includes information about Pittsburgh's South Side during the late-nineteenth and early to mid-twentieth centuries. The collection includes documents in several formats, including paper, photographs, negatives, slides, and microfilm. The information in the documents consists of family mementos, church bulletins, South Side publications, special events commemorative materials, newspaper clippings, labor information, and correspondence. The first series includes the research and organizational information of the Birmingham Union. This information was used by the Union to promote South Side development and community awareness. The second series contains the two reels of microfilmed materials included in this collection. The third series includes the photographs, negatives, and slides of places and people of the South Side during the nineteenth-century. Please note that the microfilmed information supplements the materials retained in the paper documents in the collection. Many of the same topics are documented on both paper and microfilm, but there is no overlap of specific documents in both microfilm and on paper.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Birmingham Union, 1978.
Previous Citation
Birmingham Union Collection, 1893-1977, AIS.1978.10, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Church buildings -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; South Side (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Associations, institutions, etc. -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Societies -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Societies; Church records; Birmingham Union (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- Organizational/Research Files, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains information on paper media that was gathered by the Birmingham Union about the South Side's churches, infrastructure, institutions, individuals, schools, and correspondence. Also included are flyers, publications, newspaper clippings, South Side history information, and programs generated and publicized by the Birmingham Union. The materials in this collection exist in paper form; however, additional microfilmed materials supplement each subseries.
  - Churches, 1.
    This subseries contains information from several ethnic churches located in the South Side, limited to Catholic and Protestant faiths. Bulletins, newspaper clippings, event flyers, publications, memorial booklets, rosters, histories, and directories are included. See also Series II, microfilm reels one and two, under the target entitled "Churches."
    - St. Peter's Church Special Events, 1911-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - St. Peter's Church Bulletins, 1978-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2-7)
    - Holy Cross Church, 1950-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - St. John the Evangelist, 1978, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - St. Matthew Directory, no date (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - St. Matthew Bulletins, 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
    - St. Henry's Church, 1970-1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - St. Paul's Evangelical Lutheran, 1929, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - St. Paul's Monastery (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Cobden Street Baptist Church, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - St. Mark's Episcopal Church, History by William A. Powers, no date (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Roman Catholic Church History (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Institutions and Infrastructure, 2.
    This subseries contains information about South Side institutions, such as hospitals, community organizations, businesses, government bodies, and newspapers. The subseries also contains information about the South Side's infrastructure and its development. These documents deal with the Incline and the Birmingham Bridge and Tunnel. See Series II, microfilm reel two, under the targets "Miscellaneous," and "Brashear Association" for additional information.
    - Inclines, PAT brochure, no date (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Birmingham Tunnel and Bridge, 1909-1933 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - South side Hospital, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - New South Side Markethouse Reopening, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Brashear Association, April 1940 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - birmingham Union Newsletter, "Closer Look", 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - South Side Chamber of Commerce, 1974-1992 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Education/Schools, 3.
    This subseries consists of information relating to South Side schools. Improving the schools and sports activities is the main focus of this subseries. See Series II, microfilm reel two under the target "Schools" for additional information.
    - Wickersham School Kindergarten, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 4.
    This series contains handwritten letters. The first two are in Croatian, and the final letter is in English and is about sharing memories of the historic South Side. See Series II, microfilm reel two, under the "Miscellaneous" target for correspondence between D.H. Brown and M.J. Schmalstieg.
    - Cemas to Cindich, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Birmingham Union Introspective files, 5.
    This subseries consists of information gathered by the Birmingham Union related to or supporting their role as a community organization attempting to revitalize the South Side. Some information about historic events affecting the South Side is also included. The types of materials include newspaper clippings, brochures, event flyers, history reports, and maps. Additional information can be found in series II, microfilm reel two, under the target "Miscellaneous."
    - South Side Revitalization Documentation, 1978-1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - South Side Events, 1959-1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - South Side newspaper clipping photocopies, no date (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - South Side History reports and slide presentation scripts, 1902-1956 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - World War II in the South Side, c 1940s (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Steel Strike, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Maps, c 1920 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Individuals, 6.
    This subseries covers information concerning several specific individuals and their families. These individuals were influential in the South Side. Information includes photographs (on microfilm), personal information, newspaper clippings, and articles. See also microfilm reel two under the targets "Miscellaneous" and "Photo Album."
    - John Filkovich, 1913-1978 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Anna Zgurich, no date (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Microfilm, II.
  This series contains two reels of microfilm composed of materials removed from the Birmingham Union collection of paper documents because of their brittleness. The materials span the range of the collection, covering information on churches, schools, community organizations, correspondence, pictures, newspapers, and individuals. Directories, books, newspaper clippings, and photographs are represented on these microfilm reels. Targets are included on the microfilm reels to ease research for the user. Targets and the materials contained within the target groupings are listed here.
  - South Side Community Council, 1963-1978, 1.
    - Newsletter, "South Side Lights", 1971-March 1978 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - City Planning Commission Public Hearing (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Position Statements (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Events - News clippings (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Project Proposals (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Reports (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Correspondence (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Brochures/Publications (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Photographs (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
  - South Side Community Education Committee, 2.
    - Meeting Notes and Minutes (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - South side High Questionnaire (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Reports and Recommendations (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
  - Churches, 3.
    - Presidents and Secretaries of PTG organization in 16th and 17th Ward Catholic schools, 1963 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Church Contacts (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - South Side Community Council Church Tour, 1975 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Our Lady of Fatima, High Latin Mass Broadcast Announcement (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Clergy Luncheon (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Bingham Street Methodist Church (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Holy Trinity Serbian Eastern Orthodox Church (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - St. Adalbert's Church (Sw. Wociecha R.K. Church), History (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - St. Casimir's Church (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - St. Henry's Church (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - St. Joseph's Church (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - St. Josephat (Ukrainian Catholic), "Album pa miatkowy zlotego jubileuszu parafje Sw. Joszafit" (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - St. John the Baptist Church (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - St. John the Evangelist (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - St. Mary's Church (Russian Orthodox) (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - St. Matthew's Church, St. Matthew Golden Jubilee, 1955 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - St. Michael's Church (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - St. Michael's Church Continued (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - "Spomen Kniiga" (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - St. Peter's Church (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Walton Methodist Church (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Bingham Street Methodist Church (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Second Primitive Methodist Church (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - St. James Lutheran (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - South Side Catholic Elementary Schools (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
  - Schools, 4.
    - Committee for a Comprehensive South High (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - School Board Meeting Notes and Minutes (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Improvement Proposals (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Orioles Football and Stadium (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Library Floor Plan (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 5.
    - South Side Chamber of Commerce (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - South Side Hospital (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Police-Citizens' Council News (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Inclines (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - South Side News clips (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Brashear Association, Background Material, Study of Brashear Association in Southwest Pittsburgh, 1967 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - John A. Brashear (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - South Side Revitalization Documentation (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Pittsburgh Historic and Landmarks Association Funding Campaign (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Thaddeus Moseley, 1977 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Bicentennial Reporter, June 29, 1976 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - New South Side Markethouse Dedication and Opening Souvenir Booklet, 1893 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Pittsburgh Historic and Landmarks Association, The Stones of Pittsburgh #7, "Birmingham, Pittsburgh's South Side" (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - "Birmingham (South Side)" Text by Robert K. Hayden and sketches by South Side Catholic Middle School students (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Letter: Mr. D. H. Brown to Mary Jane Schmalstieg, December 1977 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - South Side Community Church Tour, 1979 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
  - Brashear Association, 6.
    - Health and Welfare Association of Allegheny County (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Report on the Brashear Association, 1969 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
  - Photo Albums, 7.
    - Anna Zgurich, family photo albums (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
- Photographs/Negatives/Slides, III.
  This series contains photographs, negatives, and slides that document the places and people living in the South Side, mostly during the early-twentieth century. The first group of photographs deals with scenery and activities on the South Side. Individual and family photographs are contained in the second group, and photographs of larger groups and organizations are contained in the final grouping. Most folders contain several photographs in several formats, including prints, photocopies, and originals. Many of the people pictures in and the dates for these photographs are unknown. Additionally, the photographs are located in several distinct areas, including the oversize files. For the photo albums of Ms. Anna Zgurich, see microfilm reel one. Finally, many of the photographs in this collection exist as duplicates and as the same picture in different formats, such as photocopies, prints, originals, and negatives.
  - Homes restored by Pittsburgh Historic and Landmark Association, 2800 Jane St., 1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Beer Delivery Wagon, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - John Brashear, home, office, and portrait, no dates (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Brashear Association, Building, no date (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - South Side stores, c 1900-1920 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - South Side Presbyterian Church and Church Interiors (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - St. Mary's Church, no date (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - St. Peter's Church Fire Damage and New Construction, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - St. Michael's Church, no date (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Manger Scenes, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Carson and Sterling Street Scenes, c 1900-1920 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Street Scenes, Restored Homes, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Views of Pittsburgh from the South side, c 1910 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 12th Street Incline, South side, c 1900-1920 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - South Side Streetcars (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Theater, Maybe Warner (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Industrial Scenes, "Flying High in Pittsburgh," and Airport Grove Farm, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Unknown Scenes (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Philips Mine and Mill Supply Co., 1880s (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Labor/Workers, Blooming Mill, 1912, c 1930 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Mill Workers, no date (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Striking Miners, Local Union 5301, Beech Bottom, West Virginia, July 29, 192 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Musical Groups, 1910-1920 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Tamuraski Zbor "Hrvatska Mladost" Ustrojen, March 27, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Baseball, no dates (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - School Groups, c 1900-1920 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - St. Peter's Church School, 1888, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - South High Basketball Team, c 1930-1940 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Group Portraits (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Pittsburgh Company with donkey, no date (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Children, no dates (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Anton Cindrich Family, c 1920, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Sister Marie Charles, Teacher at Holy Cross, 1931-1938 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Father Kevin Keelan: rolling change; in group picture, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Jan Vucic Cindrich, no date (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Paul John Menzel, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Mary Jane Schmalstieg, First Communion, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Ks. O. Stanislaw, no date (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Wake, no date (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Wake, A. Zurich Family (in Croatia?), no date (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Marriage Portraits, 1920-1921, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Wedding Scenes (Box 3, Folder 42-44)
  - First Communion Pictures (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Casual Individuals (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Unidentified family portrait, no date (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - South side gatherings, c 1950 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Individuals - Croatia? (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Individuals, Yugoslavia (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Yugoslavia, June 1976, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - World War II individuals (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - World War I soldiers, unidentified (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - George Cindrich and the Croatian Club, c 1940s (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Individuals, Canada, c 1900-1950 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Individuals, c 1900-1950 (Box 3, Folder 56-59)
  - Negatives and Slides (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Oversize
    - St. Peter's Church, South Side, Pittsburgh, no date, 1. (Map-case 7, Drawer 3)
    - Mine equipment produced by Phillips mine and mill supply (9 prints), 2.
    - German Beneficial Union - unidentified gathering, Unidentified Musician/Dance group, outdoors, no date, February 1924; 3.
    - Jno. Phillips, with signature, 4.
    - Picture of fraternal group, 1947; 5.
    - Picture, "Testimonial Dinner for Dr. Ivan Subacicium of Croatia,", 1941; 6.
    - Picture of a wedding party, 7.
    - Picture of Musicians/Dance Team, 8.